Hello everyone. Welcome to our session
today about introducing Contoso Demo
Tool. Uh my name is Wael Abu Sa'ada. I'm
a senior software engineer at Microsoft,
and I'm joined today by
Uh hi, I'm Horan. I'm a software
engineer at Microsoft.
Awesome.
Our agenda for today is that we're going
to talk about the current demo data
tool.
Uh we'll also talk about uh Contoso.
And we will show you how you can build
your own demo data module. And then
finally, we will share our future plan
for Contoso demo data.
So, let's start with the current demo
data and the tool that we have
currently. So, as you may know, the
available demo data that comes out of
the box is set up evaluation if you are
using SaaS, extended which you can find
on-prem,
and you might be familiar with that
screenshot which is basically how you
create a new company where you can
choose this set of evaluation or you
know, uh set up data, whichever company
you would want to create, right?
So,
uh
yeah, so using rapid start package to
create your demo data is a support tool,
absolutely, but it has its own
limitation. So, let's have this
scenario, if you have a a set of
features that you want to demonstrate to
your customer, and sometimes you might
want to mix and match which feature you
want to present.
So, let's have this scenario where
you're trying to extract a subset of
demo data, and you start as an example
from evaluation package.
First thing you want to try to do is you
will try to identify which table contain
the demo data relative to your features
that you want to present.
Then, you will try to export these
tables
as our own start package, and then try
to import it again in the new company
that you created that you will use to
demonstrate your feature to your
customer. This might be a trial and
error until you get the right exact
tables that are related and, you know,
correctly applied.
And finally, you have a final package
that you can use to create multiple
company to demonstrate this set of
features. As you can see, this is not
the optimal process, right? So, that
actually led us to start
thinking about how we can improve that,
and hence introducing Contoso. So, let's
start. First, what is Contoso?
So, Contoso Coffee is a fictitious
company that produces coffee and coffee
machines.
It is an initiative across
uh Dynamics 365 products to basically
demonstrate different features and
services that we offer.
And the Contoso Coffee is not a new
thing. We actually have released it like
two uh releases ago, uh and we already
have some available modules. And in this
release, we even increasing the modules.
So, right now we're going to have
available common, warehousing,
manufacturing, service, and we are
working currently on more in or on
basically introducing more modules for
Contoso.
All right. So, when we were designing
Contoso, we had four main goals.
The first one is that we wanted to split
demo data into different modules.
Each module is supposed to be a
scenario-based.
And all the modules, all the demo data
modules, should work together and
separately.
Since we can have bunch of different
modules,
uh we might want to have also dependency
between these modules. So, let's have
that example. You're building, you know,
your demo data module and you have
dependency on chart of accounts. You
don't want to go copy the code that will
generate chart of accounts or even copy
the data and insert it again. This is
not really feasible. So, from now on
think of demo data module as LEGO and
it's like bricks of LEGO that you build
on top of each other.
Next, we split the demo data into
logical data layers. So, we start from
setup. This is basically where you
insert your, you know, unit of measure,
number theory, etc.
Master data layer where basically you
have your items, your customers, your
vendors, transactional where basically
you, I don't know, let's say post an
invoice, and then finally historical.
And
we we we we try to basically uh have
this organized in a nice way. So, we
package all of that and have it in an
interface that then you will have to
implement when you create your own demo
data module. And Haroon is going to show
you more on this later.
Finally, the whole initiative of working
on Contoso demo data is basically to
speed up productivity.
So, we had in mind that we must simplify
creating a demo data module. And again,
you will see that later how easy it is
to build your own module.
Uh
we wanted to build the tool. We did
build the tool that will be released in
this wave
to orchestrate configuring and running
different demo data modules.
Finally, we had in mind to simplify
localization and extensibility.
And if we have a high-level overview of
the architecture,
you will see that we would have we
Microsoft will build the Contoso demo
tool
and we will maintain it.
We will also release different set of
modules and we're working increasing on
increasing the amount of available
modules. So at the moment, again, common
warehousing, manufacturing and service.
And the idea is that as as we said
earlier, these are like Lego bricks, so
you can build on top of any module you
would like to. So if you building on top
of warehousing, that's easy. Just have
dependency on warehousing. All the data
will be generated behind the scene.
And now, let's show you how you can
build your own demo data module. Haroon?
Thanks, Vael. Um here I'm going to show
you how to build your own demo data
module. And to get started is fairly
simple. If you don't have an extension
already, uh just create your own
extension and update Contoso coffee demo
data set first party extension as
dependency.
And the extension is already available.
But the new Contoso demo tool will be
available from 23.0. So that's something
some detail you may want to pay
attention to.
And after that is straightforward. Go
implement your enum extension.
Uh you extend on the Contoso demo data
module. And here I'm having a demo data
dummy mode value here. Uh but yeah, just
put your own features name or scenario
name here. That's totally fine.
And then go ahead implement the
interface. And here is a set of
procedures you will have to implement.
Uh I will just go through them one by
one. So the first is conversion page. Uh
so the idea here is
if your own demo data module would want
some customer to customize what kind of
for example customers you want the demo
data to be created on, then you can ask
the
customer to specify them here.
And or if you don't want anyone to
customize your demo data, that's also
totally fine. Just leave the procedure
empty.
And the next is to specify the
dependency your module have. So here we
have the dependency on the common
module.
And well, before you actually specify
the dependencies, we highly recommend
you to go ahead and check out what data
is created in each module.
So the idea for common module is we are
trying to create a set of
demo data that will be used commonly
used for all the modules. And so for
example, we create some a small set of
chart of accounts and some posting
groups and posting setups.
Um but yeah, it's all the code will be
available on GitHub soon. So check it
out. And also, if you feel like some
modules should be included for more
data, just feel free to create an issue
or a pull request here.
And
then is the rest for procedures will be
as well demonstrated. It just create
demo data layer by layer. And yeah.
And while you are implementing the
interface, we provided a
some helpers code units to help you
speed up the process.
For example, as you can see here, we are
creating one line of general posting
setup in one line of code. That's
because we created a set of helper code
units
to help you focus on your scenario, so
you don't need to worry about populating
which field in which table. And you can
just call those code units and specify
the values in the parameters instead.
And also, you can see from this code
snapshot here,
we are having reference on common
posting group. And that's because those
posting groups are created inside the
common module. So, instead of having to
create my own posting groups, I can just
reuse the ones that's already created in
the dependencies.
And just a quick recap,
it's fairly simple three steps to create
your own demo data module. So, create
your own extension and object object the
dependency and then extend the enum and
implement the interface. So, after that
you publish or install your app. Then on
the Contoso demo tool page,
your demo module will be show up here.
And
then you can click generate
after selecting a module, of course,
click generate.
Then
all you can see your module and the
dependency module will be generated.
And that's all for me.
Awesome. Thank you, Harun. So, now on
our
future plans for Contoso demo tool and
demo data modules.
The first thing is that we want to move
toward on-demand demo data creation. So,
to get there, we definitely need to have
more modules to support basically
demonstrating different features of
Business Central.
We would also slowly start to move away
from creating our app historic package,
but again, once we have enough modules
that you can that can replace the
existing packages we have at the moment.
Finally,
you can we can this actually would allow
us to improve something like the company
creation wizard. So, instead of the
company creation wizard looking like
this,
it would look something like that.
So, you can basically when you create a
new company, you can choose a set of
modules that you want. You can basically
add that in your pipeline for running
tests or whatever,
and you can even use APIs to create your
own company with a set of modules that
you want. So, it will give you lots of
capability going forward.
Finally,
all of this is open source. It has been
open source for like a year now. And if
you have any feedback, if you have any
issues, yeah, please reach out. Open an
issue for us on GitHub. We monitor this
part of the repo closely. So,
with that, I would like to say, thank
you for listening in.
Thank you.